<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Community Whitepaper</title>

    <date>2004-08-27</date>

    <edition></edition>

    <authorgroup>
      <author>
        <firstname>Rob</firstname>

        <surname>van Maris</surname>
      </author>

      <author>
        <firstname>Rob</firstname>

        <surname>Vermeulen</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>This software is OSI Certified Open Source Software. OSI Certified
      is a certification mark of the Open Source Initiative.</para>

      <para>The license (Mozilla version 1.0) can be read at the MMBase site.
      See <ulink
      url="http://www.mmbase.org/license">http://www.mmbase.org/license</ulink></para>
    </legalnotice>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>What exactly is MMBase? How is its software organized, and how will
    it grow overtime? The number of organizations involved with MMBase is
    increasing. This presents new opportunities to share and collaborate,
    provided that questions like these are anwered. In this document, the
    MMBase Management Commitee (MMC) presents guidelines for the MMBase
    community.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>MMBase community</title>

    <para>An increasing number of people and organizations is involved with
    MMBase in some way. Together they comprise the MMBase community, an
    ecosystem surrounding MMBase and fostering new developments. In order to
    ensure a healthy community, it is vital that the roles and
    responsibilities of its citizens are clearly established. The following
    groups can be distinguished.</para>

    <section>
      <title>MMC (MMBase Management Commitee)</title>

      <para>The MMC coordinates the Open Source process, the development and
      releases of MMBase distributions. Its mission is to maintain a stable
      platform for MMBase developers, and ensure a good evolution of the
      MMBase software. To achieve its goals the MMC relies on good
      communication among the developers community.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase developers</title>

      <para>These are the developers that develop and maintain the MMBase
      distributions. Most of these are also committers, i.e. they can modify
      code in the MMBase CVS repository.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>External developers</title>

      <para>These are developers that develop software that extends the basic
      functionality of MMBase. This may be complete (web) applications or
      reusable components.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Users</title>

      <para>Finally, these are the users of the resulting software. Often they
      are also the owners of the finished applications and components, as
      these result from projects commissioned by them.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>MMBase parts</title>

    <para>In order to enable the community to contribute to the various
    software components, a distinction is made between different categories of
    components. These are the following categories.</para>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase core</title>

      <para>The MMBase core is the base of all MMBase software. It includes
      Storage and the Security interfaces, as well as the MMBase Cloud
      Interface (MMCI=Bridge), which provides a stable and backwards
      compatible interface to the (legacy) MMBase core. See Figure 1: MMBase
      Architectural Overview. Reusable software components that extend the
      functionality of the core are called packages.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase community packages</title>

      <para>MMBase community packages are packages that are maintained by the
      MMBase developers for one of several reasons:<itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
             Its use is (expected to be) widespread; 
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
             As an example; 
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
             For backwards compatibility with previous releases. 
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist> The MMC and the committers can vote about what should
      be MMBase packages.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>MMBase external packages</title>

      <para>MMBase external packages are all packages which are not MMBase
      community packages. These are typically developed by external
      developers, and fall outside the responsibility of the MMBase
      Developers.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Community process</title>

    <para>The community provides opportunities for organizations to contribute
    and collaborate. The driving force behind this proces is the fact that
    several organizations may have similar needs. Accordingly, the costs of
    developing pieces of functionality can be shared. At present these
    opportunities are not exploited to its full potential. The obstacles here
    can be of a various nature. The MMC aims to facilitate such collaboration.
    In order to do so, the MMC strives to address the technical and
    infrastructural obstacles.</para>

    <section>
      <title>Technical</title>

      <para>At present there is no easy standard way to package, distribute or
      install a package. This will be adressed by the “packages” project,
      which in the future will provide standard tools for the process.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Infrastructure</title>

      <para>The MMC maintains a list of external packages on the MMBase
      website (http://www.mmbase.org/packages). This list will include all
      contributed packages that that are brought to the attention of MMC, when
      they satisfy these requirements.</para>

      <para>Minimal requirements: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
             available for download 
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
             actively maintained 
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>Note that the minimal requirements do not require the
      software to be Open Source, even though this is encouraged.</para>

      <para>A community mailing list is available, where topics can be
      discussed related to the development of external packages. The community
      mailing list can be found at <link
      linkend="???">http://www.mmbase.org/contact</link>.</para>

      <para>The MMC and the MMBase Foundation can also be contacted with
      questions related to the development of external packages. The
      Foundation can help in gathering needs of users. The MMC can provide
      more technical related information. E.g. which parts should be developed
      as an external package and which parts should be integrated with the
      core.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Open Source</title>

      <para>When is software Open Source? There are different definitions in
      use, but a general definition is provided here: <link
      linkend="???">http://www.opensource.org/docs/definition.php</link></para>

      <para>In addition to this, the MMC recommends the following best
      practices.</para>

      <para>Recommendations: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
             documentation included 
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
             license compatible with Mozilla Public License 
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
             contact-details available of maintainer 
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>How to contribute</title>

      <para>Always a good start for developing MMBase software, is to launch
      ideas within the MMBase community. Discuss which parts of the new
      software should become an external package, and which parts should
      become part of the MMBase core, or community packages. Notify the MMBase
      community with your developments. This way it can be avoided that the
      same functionality is being made twice by different community members,
      and possibilities to collaboration can be exploited.</para>

      <para>Ask the MMC to put information about your package online when the
      package is available.</para>

      <para>For the community it’s crucial to be able to rely on packages that
      are being made available. So please don’t just offer the community
      packages hoping that others will maintain them, but maintain the package
      yourself. If you think the package is of great importance and should be
      maintained by the MMBase developers you can ask the MMBase developers to
      make it a MMBase package. The MMC and the committers will vote about
      this.</para>

      <para>Finally, you can contribute to external packages. Contacts it's
      maintainer for this.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>References</title>

    <orderedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>MMBase guidelines <link
        linkend="???">http://www.mmbase.org/guidelines</link></para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <para></para>
  </section>
</article>
